<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Scott Williams]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-21T20:39:25-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott Williams]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Madness of Errors in Swift]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2015/01/21/the-madness-of-errors-in-swift/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-21T20:18:43-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2015/01/21/the-madness-of-errors-in-swift</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let&rsquo;s take a common scenario. You are making an HTTP request and are checking the response for an error. If there is one, you&rsquo;d like to post a notification and let some error handler deal with it.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>    Alamofire.request(.GET, someURL).response { (request, response, data, error) in
</span><span class='line'>        if error != nil {
</span><span class='line'>            let userInfo = ["error": error]
</span><span class='line'>            let nc = NSNotificationCenter.defaultCenter()
</span><span class='line'>            nc.postNotificationName("HTTPERROR", object: nil, userInfo: userInfo)
</span><span class='line'>        }
</span><span class='line'>    }</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Uh oh, there&rsquo;s a compiler error on the <code>userInfo</code> argument with the message &ldquo;Extra argument &lsquo;userInfo&rsquo; in call&rdquo;. Huh? <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/Cocoa/Reference/Foundation/Classes/NSNotificationCenter_Class/index.html#//apple_ref/occ/instm/NSNotificationCenter/postNotificationName:object:userInfo:"><code>postNotificationName</code> definitely allows for a <code>userInfo</code> parameter</a>. Maybe it&rsquo;s a hidden typing error? According to the docs <code>userInfo</code> is supposed to be an optional dictionary like of type: <code>[NSObject : AnyObject]</code>. My key is a String which is bridged from <code>NSString</code>, which is an <code>NSObject</code> and <code>NSError</code> is also an <code>AnyObject</code>, so what gives?</p>

<figure class="center">
    <img alt="Lying" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/xcode-lying-cat.jpg">
    <figcaption></figcaption>
</figure>


<p>After banging my head on the wall for a while I remembered that the <code>error</code> variable from <a href="https://github.com/Alamofire/Alamofire">AlamoFire</a> is an optional. Therefore, the correct declaration for <code>userInfo</code> is to unwrap the error:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>let userInfo = ["error": error!]</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And voilà, no more compilation errors. &ldquo;Extra argument &lsquo;userInfo&rsquo; in call&rdquo; is a crappy error message. The proper one should have been something about values in the <code>userInfo</code> dictionary not being optional.</p>

<p>Swift is full of these unfortunately. Between these and your friendly SourceKit crashes it&rsquo;s getting untenable. My wish for 2015 is for Apple to address these shortcomings.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[O Christmas Roast]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/29/o-christmas-roast/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-29T15:55:42-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/29/o-christmas-roast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I posted this on Twitter. Here it is for posterity.</em></p>

<p>O Christmas Roast, O Christmas Roast!<br />
Thy rawness shall be ending<br />
O Christmas Roast, O Christmas Roast!<br />
Thy rawness shall be ending<br /></p>

<p>Inside the oven you shall go<br />
So that the juice within you flows<br />
O Christmas Roast, O Christmas Roast!<br />
Thy rawness shall be ending<br /></p>

<p>O Christmas Roast, O Christmas Roast!<br />
Such gravy will you make me!<br />
O Christmas Roast, O Christmas Roast!<br />
Such gravy will you make me!<br /></p>

<p>The thermometer will pierce your side<br />
Until your temp reads 125<br />
O Christmas Roast, O Christmas Roast!<br />
Such gravy will you make me!<br /></p>

<p>O Christmas Roast, O Christmas Roast!<br />
We&rsquo;ll set our teeth upon thee!<br />
O Christmas Roast, O Christmas Roast!<br />
We&rsquo;ll set our teeth upon thee!<br /></p>

<p>Two yards of plastic will we turn<br />
To avoid a chilling freezer burn<br />
O Christmas Roast, O Christmas Roast!<br />
We&rsquo;ll save you for another meal<br /></p>

<p>Each tasty bite<br />
Each dab of meat<br />
No other bite will fill my cheeks<br /></p>

<p>O Christmas Roast, O Christmas Roast!<br />
Within our guts digesting<br />
Within our guts digesting<br /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The iOS Development Calendarw]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/08/the-ios-development-year/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-08T14:04:40-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/08/the-ios-development-year</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>January</strong>: &ldquo;We just had our biggest sales quarter ever!&rdquo; &ndash; Apple, adding another $20B to their bank account.</p>

<p><strong>April</strong>: Speculation of what&rsquo;s gonna be in the next version of iOS.</p>

<p><strong>June</strong>: WWDC. New things! Wow! Ideas abound! Flurries of productivity. &ldquo;Guys, I think Apple&rsquo;s playing nicer with developers now!&rdquo; &ndash; some people.</p>

<p><strong>July</strong>: Wow, this beta is really beta.</p>

<p><strong>September</strong>: iOS Next ships! New iPhone! Ship your app! Bugs!</p>

<p><strong>October</strong>: Weird rejections that don&rsquo;t make any sense.</p>

<p><strong>December</strong>: Blog posts and tweets about how Apple is screwing themselves with the byzantine app review process.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Some rejections are overturned.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li class="footnote" id="fn:1">
  <p><a href="http://www.panic.com/blog/transmit-ios-1-1-1/">You are here.</a></p>
</li>
  </ol>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Things I Learned When Making a Podcast]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/03/things-i-learned-when-making-a-podcast/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-03T07:42:25-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/03/things-i-learned-when-making-a-podcast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We just published episode 2 of <a href="https://scott-williams-bc50.squarespace.com/podcast/2014/12/3/2-the-proliferation-of-duplo">the podcast</a>. I&rsquo;m still very new at this, but I&rsquo;ve already learned more than I anticipated. Most of these are forehead slappers that now you can avoid when you make your podcast.</p>

<p>If you want to do a <a href="http://thepodcastersstudio.com/tps-ep-47-recording-a-double-ender-podcast/">double-ender</a>, don&rsquo;t use Quicktime&rsquo;s built-in audio recording &ndash; it smushes all the audio into a single track. <a href="http://www.ecamm.com/mac/callrecorder/">Ecamm Call Recorder</a> or <a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/piezo/">Piezo</a> will keep them separate.</p>

<p>Have each person say something like &ldquo;Recording&rdquo; when they start recording their end of the call. This makes it orders of magnitude easier to line up the separate audio tracks during post production. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Plug your headphones directly into your microphone. Doing something else will likely lead to some nasty <a href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/02/how-to-add-a-noise-gate-in-garageband-10/">headphone bleed</a>.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re using a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Blue-Microphones-Yeti-USB-Microphone/dp/B002VA464S/ref=sr_1_1?sr=8-1&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;keywords=blue%2Byeti&amp;tag=thepetzoo-20&amp;qid=1417634348">Blue Yeti</a>, switch to Cardioid mode. It&rsquo;s the &ldquo;heart&rdquo; or &ldquo;pacman&rdquo; symbol. Turn the gain down on it too.</p>

<p>You need to <a href="https://www.apple.com/itunes/podcasts/specs.html">submit your podcast feed to Apple</a> if you want your podcast to be in iTunes (and you really want that). According to their <a href="https://www.apple.com/itunes/podcasts/creatorfaq.html">FAQ</a> it can take 24 hours for that feed to be approved. But if you submit your feed on a common US holiday week, like say the Monday before Thanksgiving, it might take significantly longer.</p>

<p>If you have something pre-made you want to say on air, write it down first because your brain will simply refuse to cooperate if you try to just remember it.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li class="footnote" id="fn:1">
  <p>Got this via <a href="http://www.theincomparable.com/theincomparable/">The Incomparable</a>, one of my absolute favorites.</p>
</li>
  </ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's Talk Photo Licensing]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/02/lets-talk-photo-licensing/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-02T15:25:09-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/02/lets-talk-photo-licensing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="center">
    <img alt="trainwreck" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/trainwreck.jpg">
    <figcaption><a href="https://flic.kr/p/5ZcYGy">&#8220;General View of Wreck, I.C.R.R., Farmer City, Ill., Oct. 5, &#8216;09&#8221;</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/caveman_92223/">Chuck Coker</a> on Flickr</figcaption>
</figure>


<p><a href="http://online.wsj.com/articles/fight-over-flickrs-use-of-photos-1416875564">Recently, Flickr started to sell photos uploaded by its users marked with the Creative Commons license that allows commercial use</a>. They&rsquo;ve taken <a href="http://www.zeldman.com/2014/11/29/flickr-is-about-to-sell-off-your-creative-commons-photos/">some</a> <a href="http://jensimmons.com/writing/i-dont-want-creative-commons-by-to-mean-you-can-rip-me-off">heat</a> for this. I understand being angry about this sudden change without much notification, but I don&rsquo;t think it&rsquo;s terribly suprising that they&rsquo;re doing this.</p>

<p>The Creative Commons <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/">license grants them plenty of rights</a>. It says in plain english, &ldquo;&hellip;copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format
for any purpose, even commercially&hellip; No additional restrictions — You may not apply legal terms or technological measures that legally restrict others from doing anything the license permits.&rdquo;</p>

<p>I used this license for the icon in <a href="http://emergencycontacts.org/">Emergency Contacts</a>. The <a href="http://thenounproject.com/term/siren/16374/">siren in it</a> was created by <a href="http://thenounproject.com/canabravatorres/">Daniel Canabrava Torres</a> and I found it by searching <a href="http://thenounproject.com/">The Noun Project</a>. I attributed him on the website and in the app, and did not pay him for it. I&rsquo;ve also used it to find photos for on this blog, like the one up top.</p>

<p>What else does that license mean? Almost anything.</p>

<p>It means that Coca-Cola could take your photo, make it part of a national campaign, put in on every billboard in the US, and not pay you a nickel. It means that Better Homes And Gardens with its <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_magazines_by_circulation#United_States">7.5 million subscribers</a> could put your photo on the cover, and not pay you anything. It means that I could scrape Flickr and sell your photos myself, and keep all the revenues. As long as you are &ldquo;attributed&rdquo; in some way, it&rsquo;s all legal.</p>

<p>Flickr requires you to set some kind of license when you upload a photo. By <em>default</em> uses the most restrictive: &ldquo;All rights reserved&rdquo; (which precludes anyone but you from selling them), making the Creative Commons option <strong>opt-in</strong>. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> You also have the opportunity to set a license on every photo when you upload it.</p>

<p>What about other websites? Here&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.facebook.com/legal/terms">Facebook&rsquo;s terms</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>For content that is covered by intellectual property rights, like photos and videos (IP content), you specifically give us the following permission, subject to your privacy and application settings: you grant us a non-exclusive, transferable, sub-licensable, royalty-free, worldwide license to use any IP content that you post on or in connection with Facebook (IP License). This IP License ends when you delete your IP content or your account unless your content has been shared with others, and they have not deleted it.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://help.instagram.com/478745558852511">Instagram</a> is nearly identical (no surprise considering they are owned by Facebook):</p>

<blockquote><p>Instagram does not claim ownership of any Content that you post on or through the Service. Instead, you hereby grant to Instagram a non-exclusive, fully paid and royalty-free, transferable, sub-licensable, worldwide license to use the Content that you post on or through the Service, subject to the Service&rsquo;s Privacy Policy, available here <a href="http://instagram.com/legal/privacy/,">http://instagram.com/legal/privacy/,</a> including but not limited to sections 3 (&ldquo;Sharing of Your Information&rdquo;), 4 (&ldquo;How We Store Your Information&rdquo;), and 5 (&ldquo;Your Choices About Your Information&rdquo;). You can choose who can view your Content and activities, including your photos, as described in the Privacy Policy.</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/tos">Twitter</a> has similar terms too:</p>

<blockquote><p>You retain your rights to any Content you submit, post or display on or through the Services. By submitting, posting or displaying Content on or through the Services, you grant us a worldwide, non-exclusive, royalty-free license (with the right to sublicense) to use, copy, reproduce, process, adapt, modify, publish, transmit, display and distribute such Content in any and all media or distribution methods (now known or later developed).</p>

<p>You agree that this license includes the right for Twitter to provide, promote, and improve the Services and to make Content submitted to or through the Services available to other companies, organizations or individuals who partner with Twitter for the syndication, broadcast, distribution or publication of such Content on other media and services, subject to our terms and conditions for such Content use.</p>

<p>Such additional uses by Twitter, or other companies, organizations or individuals who partner with Twitter, may be made with no compensation paid to you with respect to the Content that you submit, post, transmit or otherwise make available through the Services.</p>

<p>We may modify or adapt your Content in order to transmit, display or distribute it over computer networks and in various media and/or make changes to your Content as are necessary to conform and adapt that Content to any requirements or limitations of any networks, devices, services or media.</p></blockquote>

<p>You don&rsquo;t get any options when you share a photo on Facebook, Instagram, or Twitter. This is far worse. The language is loose enough that it grants them to do just about anything. If they want to sell it, they can, and keep all the proceeds.</p>

<p>In my opinion, all of these websites should make it clear what they are allowed to do with your photos, when you upload them. Right now, it&rsquo;s too obscured, and users probably aren&rsquo;t even aware of this.</p>

<p>If you really want control, and to maintain the licensing rights<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> of your photos on the Internet, you have to host them all yourself. That kind of sucks, but it is the cost of the &ldquo;social&rdquo; Internet.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li class="footnote" id="fn:1">
  <p>I created a new Flickr account to confirm this. It was All Rights Reserved by default.</p>
</li>
<li class="footnote" id="fn:2">
  <p>Note that there is absolutely nothing you can do to keep someone else from grabbing your photo and uploading it to some other place and claim ownership. I mean you could sue them, but that&#8217;s using a grenade to kill a housefly.</p>
</li>
  </ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Add a Noise Gate in GarageBand 10]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/02/how-to-add-a-noise-gate-in-garageband-10/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-02T09:11:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/02/how-to-add-a-noise-gate-in-garageband-10</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>GarageBand is a decent amateur audio editor and is also free. I use it to edit <a href="http://fronttoback.co">my podcast</a>, which has worked out ok.</p>

<p>Dealing with audio buzzing or humming can be a problem. Sometimes this can be <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spill_%28audio%29">headphone bleed</a>, or ambient noise, or anything. A <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noise_gate">noise gate</a> can fix that up pretty well if it isn&rsquo;t too loud<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. What a noise gate does is analyze your audio and mutes any sound that is below a certain volume. GarageBand has this built-in but it is a little hard to find. It&rsquo;s interface has changed over different versions, so googling around for it often yields out of date information. Here is where it is in version <strong>10</strong>.</p>

<p>First click this knobby button.</p>

<figure class="center">
    <img alt="knobby button" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/gb/knob.png">
</figure>


<p>This&rsquo;ll bring up a panel at the bottom with some additional controls. Click the information &ldquo;i&rdquo; button, turn off &ldquo;Master&rdquo;, and click &ldquo;Controls&rdquo; from the segmented control.</p>

<figure class="center">
    <img alt="controls" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/gb/controls.png">
</figure>


<p>Finally, you&rsquo;ll have a checkbox labeled &ldquo;Noise Gate&rdquo; in that info side panel. Check it to turn it on, and use the slider to adjust how big of a gate you want.</p>

<figure class="center">
    <img alt="noise gate" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/gb/noise-gate.png">
</figure>


<p>This will set the gate on the <em>entire</em> track that is selected up in the main UI. You can have different gates for different tracks, but I don&rsquo;t think you can different ones on a single track in GarageBand.</p>

<p>Once I scrape together a little more cash I might go out and get <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/logic-pro-x/id634148309?mt=12&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11lxUn">Logic Pro</a>. For now though, GarageBand works well enough.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li class="footnote" id="fn:1">
  <p>Shoutout to <a href="https://twitter.com/jmetzendorf">Jim Metzendorf</a> for helping me out with this.</p>
</li>
  </ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My New Podcast]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/01/my-new-podcast/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-01T14:37:23-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/01/my-new-podcast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been a fan of podcasts for ages. I listened to <a href="http://grantland.com/podcasts/bs-report/">Bill Simmons&rsquo;s show</a> since it was called &ldquo;Eye of the Sports Guy&rdquo;. I listened to <a href="http://5by5.tv">Dan Benjamin&rsquo;s</a> shows before he made 5by5. About half of my t-shirts are ads for podcasts. So, when some friends asked if I wanted to make a podcast, I jumped at the chance.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a show about fathers raising their daughters. Our discussions range from the goofy stuff our girls do, to the idea that we need to maintain our masculinity being the sole male in the family, to heavier topics. We&rsquo;re calling it <a href="http://fronttoback.co">Front to Back</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. You can get it on <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/front-to-back/id945174610?mt=2">iTunes here</a>.</p>

<figure class="pull-right">
  <a href="http://fronttoback.co"><img alt="Front to Back art" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/f2b-art.png" /></a>
</figure>


<p>I&rsquo;m co-hosting it along with my Internet friends <a href="http://jeffmueller.net">Jeff</a> and <a href="http://samdavies.me">Sam</a>. Right now we are aiming to record every other week. The first episode is a shade over half an hour, which seems like a pretty good duration to me.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s gonna be a learning experience too. Going into this, none of us had ever recorded a podcast. I&rsquo;ve already learned more than I expected about production and audio editing. Watch this space because I&rsquo;m going to write about that process too. We&rsquo;re going to make a bunch of mistakes, but I think we have something here.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li class="footnote" id="fn:1">
  <p>Yeah, it references *that*.</p>
</li>
  </ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Star Wars Episode VII Soundtrack Titles]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/30/star-wars-episode-vii-soundtrack-titles/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-30T14:25:47-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/30/star-wars-episode-vii-soundtrack-titles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found the names of the songs on the Force Awakens Soundtrack. Don&rsquo;t worry, no spoilers. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<ol>
<li>20th Century Fox Theme</li>
<li>Star Wars Main Theme</li>
<li>Luke&rsquo;s Noble End</li>
<li>Luke&rsquo;s Funeral</li>
<li>Han&rsquo;s Funeral</li>
<li>Luke&rsquo;s Funeral (reprise)</li>
<li>Luke&rsquo;s Funeral Again</li>
<li>A Cube Death Star?</li>
<li>Luke&rsquo;s Funeral</li>
<li>Falcon&rsquo;s Funeral</li>
<li>Constructing a New Lightsaber</li>
<li>Return of a Jedi Master</li>
<li>Luke&rsquo;s Funeral</li>
<li>Darth Fangy Rises</li>
<li>Darth Fangy&rsquo;s Funeral</li>
<li>Chewbacca Sandwich</li>
<li>Victory Fanfare</li>
<li>Luke&rsquo;s Funeral</li>
<li>Luke&rsquo;s Funeral</li>
<li>Luke&rsquo;s Funeral</li>
<li>End Credits</li>
</ol>


<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li class="footnote" id="fn:1">
  <p>For those of you who don&#8217;t get the joke, <a href="http://www.cracked.com/blog/the-5-most-ridiculous-ways-studios-spoiled-their-own-movies/">read this</a>.</p>
</li>
  </ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Copying the Current Page From Safari]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/19/copying-the-current-page-from-safari/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-19T13:22:16-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/19/copying-the-current-page-from-safari</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If I&rsquo;m preparing a bunch of links for a blog post or something, it&rsquo;d speed things up if I could hit a button and have the computer do everything for me. Here&rsquo;s an <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/mac/documentation/AppleScript/Conceptual/AppleScriptLangGuide/introduction/ASLR_intro.html">AppleScript</a> to do just that.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='applescript'><span class='line'><span class="k">tell</span> <span class="nb">application</span> <span class="s2">&quot;Safari&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">set</span> <span class="nv">theURL</span> <span class="k">to</span> <span class="nv">URL</span> <span class="k">of</span> <span class="nv">current</span> <span class="no">tab</span> <span class="k">of</span> <span class="na">window</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">set</span> <span class="nv">theTitle</span> <span class="k">to</span> <span class="na">name</span> <span class="k">of</span> <span class="nv">current</span> <span class="no">tab</span> <span class="k">of</span> <span class="na">window</span> <span class="mi">1</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="nb">set the clipboard to</span> <span class="s2">&quot;[&quot;</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span> <span class="nv">theTitle</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span> <span class="s2">&quot;](&quot;</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span> <span class="nv">theURL</span> <span class="o">&amp;</span> <span class="s2">&quot;)&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">end</span> <span class="k">tell</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>That&rsquo;ll copy the URL and title of the current tab in Safari as a nicely formatted <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a> link. I tied that into a <a href="http://www.keyboardmaestro.com/main/">Keyboard Maestro</a> shortcut, so that I can quickly make the link with ⌘⌥⌃C, then paste it into whichever document I&rsquo;m working in.</p>

<p>This&rsquo;ll probably work with Chrome too, but I don&rsquo;t know how much it supports AppleScript.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Holiday Meals Ranked in Order of Meal Glory]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/17/holiday-meals-ranked-in-order-of-meal-glory/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T09:07:33-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/17/holiday-meals-ranked-in-order-of-meal-glory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Family is cool and all, but really, the reason we have holidays in AMERICA is to eat too much. Here&rsquo;s how they rank. This is not opinion, it is fact.</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Thanksgiving</strong>. Turkey. We do it two ways, the traditional bake, and also a smoked one. Dressing/Stuffing. Potatoes. Pies (never have just one). Everything else. Part of the romanticism for Thanksgiving is also everything that goes with it: family (I happen to like mine), friends, football, cool weather, cooking, showing my kids how to cook. Leftovers are critical: More turkey, turkey soup, turkey sandwiches, more potatoes and stuffing. Here&#8217;s how much we love Thanksgiving in the Williams house: we make a second Thanksgiving meal before Christmas. Speaking of:</li>
</ol>


<ol start="2">
<li><strong>Christmas</strong>. Roast beef (garlic + rosemary). More potatoes. More Pie. Pudding.</li>
</ol>




<ol start="3">
<li><strong>Memorial Day/Independence Day/Labor Day</strong>. From a meal perspective, these are pretty much the same. Grill and/or barbecue. Beer. Diversity amongst the meat is good.</li>
</ol>




<ol start="6">
<li><strong>Octoberfest</strong>. Bratwurst on crusty rolls with sauerkraut and super grainy mustard. Beer. No it&#8217;s not a &#8220;real&#8221; holiday, congratulations on pointing that one out. You&#8217;re a regular Columbo, you are.</li>
</ol>


<ol start="50">
<li><strong>Easter</strong>. Ham. I like various pig derived food products, but baked ham just isn&#8217;t as good. Eggs are fine and I eat them all the time, but it&#8217;s hard to make them extra &#8220;special&#8221;. How often do you cook a turkey for 8 hours during the year? Compare that to eggs.</li>
</ol>


<p>Once again, the logic here is flawless. No conjecture. For realsies.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Once Caught a Comet that was THIS Big]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/14/i-once-caught-a-comet-that-was-this-big/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-14T19:56:14-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/14/i-once-caught-a-comet-that-was-this-big</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.theguardian.com/science/gallery/2014/nov/12/rosetta-mission-lands-philae-probe-on-67p-comet-in-pictures">We landed a spacecraft on a comet</a>. This in itself is pretty cool, but apparently not many people are familiar with the size of the comet in question. These images might just help.</p>

<figure class="center">
    <img alt="Star Destroyer" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/philae-star-destroyer.jpg" style="width:350px">
    <figcaption>Via the Washington Post</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure class="center">
    <img alt="Star Trek" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/philae-startrek.jpg">
    <figcaption>Star Wars not your thing? We got you covered.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure class="center"> 
    <img alt="Rome" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/philae-rome.jpg">
    <figcaption>Keep it on Earth? Ok.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure class="center">
    <img alt="LA" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/comet_v_la.png">
    <figcaption>How &#8216;bout some AMERICA?</figcaption>
</figure>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on App Store Beta Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/11/thoughts-on-app-store-beta-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-11T19:37:07-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/11/thoughts-on-app-store-beta-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A little while ago Apple <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2014/02/21/rumor-testflight-owner-burstly-is-being-acquired-by-apple/">acquired the parent company</a> of <a href="http://testflightapp.com/">TestFlight</a> and began integrating its beta testing services into the iOS development ecosystem for iOS 8. Whenever there&rsquo;s a change to iOS there are always &ldquo;gotchas&rdquo;  and this was no exception: every app submitted as a beta still has to go through review.</p>

<p>This has been an ongoing topic on the <a href="http://www.relay.fm/upgrade">Upgrade podcast</a>. I recently submitted an update for <a href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/06/app-number-2-emergency-contacts/">Emergency Contacts</a> and decided to finally check this out myself. It took about 24 hours for the beta to be approved. I voiced my concern of this to the hosts:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>.<a href="https://twitter.com/jsnell">@jsnell</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/imyke">@imyke</a> Took about 24 hours from time of uploading a build to it passing review for a TestFlight beta. Much too long in my opinion.</p>&mdash; Scott Williams (@swilliams) <a href="https://twitter.com/swilliams/status/530898595550339073">November 8, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="http://blog.swilliams.me//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>And got a shout out on <a href="http://www.relay.fm/upgrade/9">episode #9</a> at the <a href="https://overcast.fm/podcasts/episode/244136329243311#t=1550">25:51 mark</a> (edited for length):</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Myke Hurley</strong> — In his opinion that&rsquo;s too long&hellip; I hadn&rsquo;t thought of it that way. We&rsquo;d been previously saying &ldquo;Oh how great, 24 hours is perfectly fine.&rdquo; But, maybe you just want to get it out immediately, which is what you&rsquo;re used to. So 24 hours is 24 hours longer than 10 seconds.</p>

<p><strong>Jason Snell</strong> — You get all of the extra features of that. <a href="http://hockeyapp.net/">HockeyApp</a> is still out there. The idea of Apple&rsquo;s TestFlight is that it&rsquo;s got all these other advantages going for it, including linking it to an id instead of a device id. But yeah, it&rsquo;ll be interesting to see how it goes and if it settles down over time.</p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s impossible to add nuance to Twitter, so I figured I could expand on my thought here. As a developer, I value this virtuous cycle:</p>

<figure class="center">
    <img alt="Virtuous Cycle" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/dev-virtuous-cycle.png">
</figure>


<p>When things work properly it creates a nice feedback loop and encourages me to keep going. Taking an entire day off between one of those steps resets momentum back to 0, and at least for me, momentum is huge.</p>

<p>But, like Jason said, I think Apple&rsquo;s TestFlight offers compelling advantages, especially when compared to TestFlight&rsquo;s old service. The ability to upload a build right from Xcode without having to mess around with archives and symlinks is huge. I think the UI in iTunes Connect is better too. So the $64,000 question is, Whatcha Gonna Do About It?</p>

<p>After mulling over it for a little while I think I&rsquo;ll start to switch over to Apple&rsquo;s TestFlight. In my <a href="http://swilliams.me">consulting work</a>, walking clients through the UDID process was painful and fraught with peril. I&rsquo;ll have to educate them that their builds will take a while even though I&rsquo;m &ldquo;done,&rdquo; but that&rsquo;s still less of a headache than the old way.</p>

<p><a href="http://appreviewtimes.com">App review time</a> tends to get longer at certain intervals (new iPhones and Christmas), but picks back up as the staff works through the deluge of apps. I remain hopeful that beta review will follow suit.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pricing for Emergency Contacts]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/07/pricing-for-emergency-contacts/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-07T15:15:57-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/07/pricing-for-emergency-contacts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Pricing is tricky for mobile apps these days. When I was <a href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/06/app-number-2-emergency-contacts/">developing Emergency Contacts</a>, I knew I had a few options to choose from:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Free</strong> — The app didn&rsquo;t take too long to make, but I wasn&rsquo;t sure that I wanted to just give it away for free. I thought that it had provided a modest amount of utility, so I figured that just straight up free wouldn&rsquo;t work.</li>
<li><strong>Free with an In-App Purchase</strong> — I did this with <a href="http://zartbonk.com">Zartbonk</a>. But since the feature set on Emergency Contacts is pretty small, I couldn&rsquo;t think of what to lock in an extra purchase.</li>
<li><strong>Free with ads</strong> — I just don&rsquo;t like ads in apps. I didn&rsquo;t even look to see how to get this set up.</li>
<li><strong>Paid</strong> — The choice was really between free and $0.99. Since I had ruled out free, that left me here.</li>
</ul>


<p>Figuring out pricing is hard. I think I made the right choice here, though with a more complex app, I&rsquo;m not sure if I&rsquo;d do the same thing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[App #2 - Emergency Contacts]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/06/app-number-2-emergency-contacts/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-06T14:16:17-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/11/06/app-number-2-emergency-contacts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I made <a href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2013/12/16/i-made-an-app/">another</a> App(!)</p>

<figure class="pull-right">
    <img alt="Emergency Contacts screenshot" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/ec-screenshot.png">
</figure>


<p>It&rsquo;s called <a href="http://emergencycontacts.org/">Emergency Contacts</a> and is available for your iOS 8 device. It&rsquo;s a real fast way to display information that might come in handy when things go bad. You can display an emergency contact, medical information, or whatever you&rsquo;d like in three rows of text. It displays as a widget on the <a href="http://www.imore.com/how-use-today-view-widgets-ios-8">Today View</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/emergency-contacts-ice-widget/id931010448?ls=1&amp;mt=8">Get it now for just $0.99</a>. Read on if you want to hear the origin story.</p>

<p>The idea originated from my mother-in-law. She is new to the iPhone and asked me if there was a way to display an emergency contact, since she had something like that in her old feature-phone. Other than adding text to your wallpaper (which is pretty cheesy) I didn&rsquo;t have an answer. About an hour later it hit, <em>hey, I bet it would be real simple to put that stuff on the Today screen.</em></p>

<p>It took about 3 days of programming time, most of which was sunk by fighting with <a href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/10/30/dealing-with-xcode-and-swift/">Xcode+Swift issues</a>, and iOS 8 bugs<sup>1</sup>. Probably another day or so to put together a simple website and icon. Then about 4 excruciating hours of getting all the screenshots necessary for the App Store.<sup>2</sup></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t expect this to make me rich, but felt it would be worth at least a few days of my time. I hope you like it.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<p><small>
1. Ever wanted to hide one of the navigation buttons on a `ABPeoplePickerNavigationController`? <a href="http://openradar.appspot.com/radar?id=5234709428699136">You used to be able to in iOS 7, not so much in 8</a>.
</small></p>
<p><small>
2. You have a 3.5&#8221; device, a 4&#8221; device, a 4.7&#8221; device, and a 5.5&#8221; device. And nowadays you can&#8217;t have anything in the status bar for a screenshot. You can&#8217;t just crop it out though. So, once you&#8217;ve gone to the effort of setting up the same state on 4 devices, you have to crack open Photoshop and properly airbrush out the status bar. This is extra fun when doing a Today View screenshot, because everything is nice and blurry underneath the status bar, and a giant black rectangle would be every noticeable. Even with just 2 screenshots per device, I wanted to die so bad.
</small></p>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dealing with Xcode and Swift]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/10/30/dealing-with-xcode-and-swift/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-30T10:46:09-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/10/30/dealing-with-xcode-and-swift</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/09/10/thoughts-on-swift/">I like Swift</a>. But Xcode&rsquo;s support of Swift is&hellip; lacking (to be polite).</p>

<p>My biggest woe is that code completion up and vanishes in projects. This is especially problematic when dealing with Cocoa libraries because method names tend to be verbose and descriptive. I find myself thinking &ldquo;I know it&rsquo;s called <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/DOCUMENTATION/UIKit/Reference/UINavigationController_Class/index.html#//apple_ref/occ/instm/UINavigationController/popToRootViewControllerAnimated:">popToRoot-something-somthing</a> and was it on UIViewController or the navigationController?&rdquo;. What would&rsquo;ve taken two seconds of poking through code-completion to figure that out turned into a solid minute of searching documentation. Multiply this every time you can&rsquo;t explicitly remember every part of a method call (and spell it correctly) and tasks that normally take an hour are now a significant part of a day.</p>

<p>The tools that Apple provides are now hindering development. I&rsquo;m not alone in that sentiment. On Apple&rsquo;s developer forums (account needed to view) there are a few threads with names like <a href="https://devforums.apple.com/message/1067119#1067119">&ldquo;Can SourceKit possibly crash more often on a Swift project?&rdquo;</a> and <a href="https://devforums.apple.com/thread/248397?start=0&amp;tstart=0">&ldquo;Xcode 6.1b3 Swift editing is becoming very difficult&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<p>One of those threads recommends deleting two folders: <code>~/Library/Developer/Xcode/DerivedData</code> and <code>~/Library/Caches/com.apple.dt.Xcode</code>. This does the job for me. It happens often enough that I created a hot key for it with <a href="http://www.keyboardmaestro.com/main/">Keyboard Maestro</a>.</p>

<figure class="center">
    <img alt="Keyboard Maestro Screenshot" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/xcode-swift-maestro.png">
    <figcaption>This will yell at you if those folders don&#8217;t exist, but I can live with that.</figcaption>
</figure>


<p>You could do something similar with <a href="http://www.alfredapp.com/">Alfred</a> or any other launcher type of app.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s kind of sad that I have to create this kind of shortcut to maintain my sanity, but I remain hopeful. If Apple is betting big on Swift (and I think they are), then they&rsquo;ll <em>have</em> to improve the tool support for it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[X-Wing Nostalgia]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/10/28/x-wing-nostalgia/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-28T10:38:07-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/10/28/x-wing-nostalgia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure>
    <img alt="X-Wing" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/xwing.jpg">
    <figcaption></figcaption>
</figure>


<p>X-Wing was one of my favorite games when I was a kid.</p>

<p>I played it on my <a href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/01/09/my-computers-through-the-ages/">family&rsquo;s rather old 386</a>. It didn&rsquo;t have a CD-ROM drive, and didn&rsquo;t really have a &ldquo;gaming&rdquo; sound card, which meant the sounds were primarily bleeps and bloops. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(1993_video_game)">Doom</a> ran if you shrank the screen size down to postage stamp dimensions. I was able to reduce the graphics quality of X-Wing enough to make it playable.</p>

<p>And play it I did. I didn&rsquo;t have a joystick, but managed to get along well enough with the mouse<sup>1</sup>. At one point I decided that I would kill every single enemy in the game that was killable. This meant hanging around after missions ended to attack the additional TIE Fighters/Bombers/Interceptors they would send after you to &ldquo;encourage&rdquo; you to wrap it up. It also meant attacking the <a href="http://starwars.wikia.com/wiki/EF76_Nebulon-B_escort_frigate">Frigates</a> and <a href="http://starwars.wikia.com/wiki/Star_Destroyer">Star Destroyers</a>, usually by myself. I managed to pull it off in the first campaign but gave up shortly after that.</p>

<p>At some point I realized that you could have multiple accounts in the game. And those other accounts could be your wingmen in missions. So I took my best pilot, copied it several times over, then added them back to the game so that every wingman I had was at the Top Ace level.</p>

<p>TIE Fighter was also an important game for me, though by the time I got it (and a computer that would run it) I was getting ready for college and wasn&rsquo;t as obsessive as only a 14 year old Star Wars fanatic could be.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.gog.com/game/star_wars_xwing_special_edition">Both</a> <a href="http://www.gog.com/game/star_wars_tie_fighter_special_edition">games</a> are now on sale at gog.com. I don&rsquo;t know if I have the time to go back and try to relive the glory days, but I&rsquo;m awfully tempted.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
<p><small>
1. A friend marveled at this. &#8220;I don&#8217;t know how you got through the Death Star with <em>a mouse</em>&#8221;.
</small></p>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best Customer Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/10/15/the-best-customer-service/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T11:09:22-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/10/15/the-best-customer-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few years ago I was at a steakhouse for a company dinner. I had ordered the King of Steaks, a Rib-Eye medium rare and was looking forward to eating it. When I cut into my steak I saw that it was basically well-done (there was the tiniest sliver of pink left amidst a sea of gray). I flagged the server and said &ldquo;Um, I ordered this medium-rare&hellip;&rdquo;<sup>1</sup></p>

<p>Without a moment&rsquo;s hesitation she apologized, grabbed the plate and went directly back to the kitchen with it. Barely five minutes later she brought back out a piping hot steak that was cooked <em>perfectly</em>. She checked back again a few minutes later to make sure everything was ok (it was).</p>

<p>Why was this so good? She knew exactly what had happened and knew how to fix it to my satisfaction. There weren&rsquo;t any games played, just immediate and decisive action.</p>

<p>I was at a hotel recently and the last day something bad happened that left a sour taste in my mouth. The manager on duty very nice and apologetic. But she asked &ldquo;What would you like me to do to &lsquo;make it right&rsquo;?&rdquo;. I hate that question because I don&rsquo;t know how to respond. Asking to comp the whole trip would be overboard and unfair. But putting the onus of the decision on me when I&rsquo;m already under duress only compounds the problem.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re in the service industry, you need to understand what that means and not make the customer come up with their own solutions.</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<p><small>
1. There could&rsquo;ve been a dozen reasons why my steak was overcooked, and it probably wasn&rsquo;t the server&rsquo;s fault, so there&rsquo;s no use in getting angry with her about it. The best part is that I didn&rsquo;t even have time to get angry.
</small></p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thoughts on Swift]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/09/10/thoughts-on-swift/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-10T08:24:30-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/09/10/thoughts-on-swift</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure class="center">
    <img src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/swift-logo.png" alt="Swift Logo" />
    <figcaption></figcaption>
</figure>


<p>Swift is a new language developed by Apple. I&rsquo;ve been using for a few side projects.</p>

<p>On my first glance, I thought Swift would be a great language for beginners. I&rsquo;m not 100% sure if that&rsquo;s still the case. A beginner language should push you into a positive feedback loop: do something, see it work, do some more, and so on. Swift and Xcode 6 do some of this with aplomb, especially with playgrounds, but I found some features of the language can be frustrating until you have a deeper understanding of what&rsquo;s going on.</p>

<p>Optionals are the biggest part of that. They&rsquo;re kind of crazy at first. Lot&rsquo;s of ?&rsquo;s and !&rsquo;s running around. When I was starting with Swift, Xcode would constantly complain that I was missing one. Sometimes it would tell me which one was missing, but sometimes it didn&rsquo;t. After reading the documentation a little more and thinking about it, things started to click. Handling nil values is important in any language, and handling them poorly can lead to some truly marvelous bugs or security issues. Swift makes you face them much earlier in the process. I think this is a good thing, though it can make for a frustrating start. It&rsquo;s also made me think if I&rsquo;m handling nils properly in other languages I use.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m still working on my own personal style, but I think I should be using more computed properties. A rule I&rsquo;m toying with is to keep on making methods for &ldquo;verbs&rdquo; like <code>moveFileToThing</code>, but use properties for &ldquo;nouns&rdquo; like <code>allSampleAssets</code>, even if that property makes several other calls within its implementation. This might require renaming certain methods in order to better comply with that style; if <code>allSampleAssets</code> took a <code>sort</code> parameter it couldn&rsquo;t be a property, so I&rsquo;d rename it to <code>queryAllSampleAssets(sort: NSSortDescriptor)</code>.</p>

<p>Even though it&rsquo;s a brand new thing, there is still a good amount of Objective C and Cocoa baggage. The standard collections use <code>AnyObject</code> where <code>id</code> used to be, which means you&rsquo;ll need to do some explicit casting to the type you need. I found it easier when dealing with an <code>NSDictionary</code> or <code>NSArray</code> to not try to cram all the casting and then manipulating into a single line of code.</p>

<p>Enums have reams of power that could be used for evil. I like the way <a href="http://nsscreencast.com/episodes/130-swift-json-redux-part-1">NSScreencasts uses enums with JSON parsing</a>, but it&rsquo;s hard to comprehend. If you have more of a functional programming background, I suspect this would be easier.</p>

<p>Swift is going to be huge. I think Apple does have a language on its hands that&rsquo;ll last for its next 20 years. There are still some rough edges and potential pitfalls, but It has become the language I prefer when creating iOS apps.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Trip to Joshua Tree and Back]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/09/07/a-trip-to-joshua-tree-and-back/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-07T14:23:14-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/09/07/a-trip-to-joshua-tree-and-back</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>[Editor&rsquo;s note: the author will try not to make any terrible <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Joshua_Tree">U2</a> jokes, but no guarantees, k?]</em></p>

<p>On drive back from visiting my grandfather in Palm Springs, I started to notice a few interesting spots right off of I-10. I got to thinking that even though I&rsquo;ve driven that stretch of road dozens of times I&rsquo;ve never seen what&rsquo;s just down the various exits. When I got home I asked a friend if he wanted to go with me on an adventure, we set a date and went off.</p>

<p>I decided that I didn&rsquo;t have enough stress on my wallet and rented an amazing <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00LAJQVR6/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B00LAJQVR6&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=thepetzoo-20&amp;linkId=SXRLLGQXQE6EXCZV">Nikon D800</a> with a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0037KM0X0/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B0037KM0X0&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=thepetzoo-20&amp;linkId=WKK5Q3JEYBRTBVUG">lens</a> to go with it.</p>

<p>I was blown away by the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_range">dynamic range</a> of the D800. I thought I&rsquo;d appreciate the step in quality over my older D300, but wow! I haven&rsquo;t had the opportunity to use a <a href="http://zackarias.com/for-photographers/gear-gadgets/why-i-moved-to-medium-format-phase-one-iq140-review/">medium format setup</a>, but I think I understand just how much of a jump in quality a larger sensor size can make.</p>

<p>Anyways, here&rsquo;s our journey.</p>

<h3>Salome Rd, North off I-10</h3>

<figure>
    <img alt="Shed" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1300.jpg">
    <figcaption>Some kind of utility shed off of Salome Rd</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Cactus" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1313.jpg">
    <figcaption>I&#8217;m not totally sold on the value of having a maximum aperture of f/1.4 on a 24mm lens, but this cactus demonstrates that it can look pretty. Also further down Salome Rd, then Eagle Eye Rd.</figcaption>
</figure>


<h3>Out Past Blythe</h3>

<figure>
    <img alt="No Hunting" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1343.jpg">
    <figcaption>Blythe is a town that people usually stop in for lunch on their way to California or Arizona. We decided to see what&#8217;s out on the roads that go beyond the fast food.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Rusted Car" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1370.jpg">
    <figcaption>According to Apple Maps, Lovekin Rd is supposed to go all the way up to Highway 62. I&#8217;m sure it does, but at about 3/4&#8217;s of the way it becomes a private road and is no longer paved. This rusted out hulk was about 100 yards away from the end.</figcaption>
</figure>


<h3>Storm and Desert Center</h3>

<figure>
    <img alt="Storm Comin'" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1374.jpg">
    <figcaption>Back on I-10. We saw a big weather system moving in and managed to get onto an overpass before it hit us.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Decay" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1383.jpg">
    <figcaption><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desert_Center,_California">Desert Center</a> is what gave me the idea to do this trip in the first place. Most of the town looks abandoned, and yields some pretty interesting photo locations.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Family Cafe" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1392.jpg">
    <figcaption>It was pouring at this point, but I did manage to run out in the rain long enough to grab this.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Old Gas Pump" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1402.jpg">
    <figcaption>Next to the café was an ancient gas station. Each of the pumps were in various stages of decay.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Chevron Supreme" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1410.jpg">
    <figcaption>Chevron Supreme!</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Squatted" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1423.jpg">
    <figcaption>A little west of of the cafe was a group of pre-fabricated houses, kind of like what you&#8217;d see from Habitat for Humanity. All of them were basically destroyed from neglect and looked like a refuge for squatters.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Tagged" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1428.jpg">
    <figcaption>All of them were vandalized too.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Desert" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1432.jpg">
    <figcaption>To escape the weather we headed north from Desert Center up Highway 177. In the distance you could see the dust blowing against the mountains.</figcaption>
</figure>


<h3>Joshua Tree Park</h3>

<p>I finally found what I was looking for. <em>[ed. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EabB55IYyOg">Argh!</a> You were warned.]</em></p>

<figure>
    <img alt="Joshua Tree" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1464.jpg">
    <figcaption>Joshua Trees are interesting. They look like palms trees, but with multiple heads.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Joshua Tree" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1473.jpg">
    <figcaption>This is the Dynamic Range I was talking about. The sun is literally right behind the tree, but you can still make out plenty of detail in the shadows.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Fat caterpillar" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1505.jpg">
    <figcaption>We also found lot&#8217;s of fat caterpillars. This guy looked like he was getting ready to do the chrysalis thing.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Jumbo Rocks" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1515.jpg">
    <figcaption>If you like bouldering or climbing rocks, this would be the place for you. After this trip, I want to return and camp there to be able to explore all of its crannies.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Joshua Tree" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1522.jpg">
    <figcaption>By this point I was coming up with various schemes to justify keeping the D800.</figcaption>
</figure>




<figure>
    <img alt="Joshua Tree" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1530.jpg">
    <figcaption>Yup.</figcaption>
</figure>


<h3>Coming Home</h3>

<figure>
    <img alt="My Scion" src="http://swilliams.me/static/photos/joshua-tree/800_1545.jpg">
    <figcaption>We drove <a href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2013/04/20/in-which-i-purchased-a-new-car/">my car</a> The way out of the park back down to I-10 was filled corners and S-curves. Needless to say, I loved it.</figcaption>
</figure>


<p>Oh, and if you like these, did you know that I have a <a href="http://swilliamsphoto.com">photoblog</a>? You should follow it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Performance Detractors]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/09/04/performance-detractors/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-04T09:07:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/09/04/performance-detractors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>PED&rsquo;s are one of the long-time kerfuffles in sports. I had a thought about how to solve that controversy the other day.</p>

<p>First, embrace PEDs. Stop suspending athletes for taking them and make everything public. <em>Just pay them less.</em> If PEDs make the game easier for them, don&rsquo;t pay them as much.</p>

<p>Next, encourage Performance <em>Detractors</em> by paying athletes more for using them. If a linebacker can make 15 sacks while on 20mg of Valium, he should be paid more. You could have a whole range.</p>

<ul>
<li>-50% for the horse steroids used by the East Germans in the 80s</li>
<li>-30% for the Lance Armstrong&rsquo;s Blood Doping Special</li>
<li>-20% for all the Biogensis type stuff</li>
<li>-1% for Ibuprofen</li>
<li>Control group. No drugs at all.</li>
<li>+10% Marijuana</li>
<li>+20% Benzodiazepines</li>
<li>+40% LSD</li>
</ul>


<p>Because who wouldn&rsquo;t be entertained by a bunch of oversized men tripping on LSD trying to play football? Roger Goodell, you can use the links in the left sidebar to contact me for terms on where to send a check.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
