<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Code | Scott Williams]]></title>
  <link href="http://swilliams.github.io/words/categories/code/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://swilliams.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-05T10:26:48-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://swilliams.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott Williams]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Migrating From Squarespace]]></title>
    <link href="http://swilliams.github.io/words/2014/03/05/migrating-from-squarespace/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T09:23:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://swilliams.github.io/words/2014/03/05/migrating-from-squarespace</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Squarespace is a popular service to host a website or blog. You might have seen their <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S0Or1f_RxKQ">Super Bowl commercial</a> or heard about them on one of the hundred podcasts they sponsor. I signed up about a year and a half ago and used it as my main blog. I&rsquo;ve decided to move away and use <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> to host my blog on <a href="http://octopress.org/">GitHub Pages</a> instead.</p>

<p>Why? Well, for starters, it&rsquo;s slow to use. I think it&rsquo;s a byproduct of the way they organized their <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-page_application">single-page application</a> architecture. I find myself having to wait for things to open in modal windows, or to load another menu.</p>

<p>The layout tools are bad. If all you do is write text and link to stuff, this doesn&rsquo;t matter. Sometimes I like to have <a href="/words/2014/01/26/demystifying-ruby-dsls">in depth coding posts</a> that have multiple blocks of code within them. This is incredibly painful to do with the Squarespace layout tools. Here&rsquo;s the process:</p>

<ol>
<li>Hover over an existing text block.</li>
<li>Click the appropriate &ldquo;+&rdquo; button.</li>
<li>Scroll down to find the &ldquo;CODE&rdquo; button.</li>
<li>Paste in the code (after making sure the indentation is correct)</li>
<li>Go to step 1 and this time, select Markdown.</li>
<li>Rinse and repeat for <em>every</em> block and image you want.</li>
</ol>


<p>What you see is <em>definitely not</em> what you get. Sizing images to align to the left or right of a paragraph is awful. For some reason, the editing font on the admin page is different than the one on the actual site. This means that even if everything lines up on the admin page, it might not on the live site. Fixing this is tedious. Again, due to the single-pagedness of the admin site, you can&rsquo;t easiliy open the preview in a new tab or window (&lsquo;Open in new page&rsquo; does nothing). You need to open a brand new browser window, navigate to your admin site, then click on the preview button there.</p>

<p>Saving a post in the editor closes the modal that contains it. This means that the workflow for making any kind of adjustment is:</p>

<ol>
<li>Do the thing above to get a second window open to look at the preview.</li>
<li>Click the post in the first window to edit.</li>
<li>Wait a second.</li>
<li>Find the typo to fix. This is extra fun if you have multiple blocks of text.</li>
<li>Fix the typo and hit save. (Modal closes)</li>
<li>Switch over to the preview in the second window and refresh.</li>
<li>If it&rsquo;s not right, repeat steps 2-6 until it is.</li>
</ol>


<p>All of this for about $100/year (or more).</p>

<p>Octopress is a static site generator that is aimed at developers. If you don&rsquo;t know <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a>, <a href="http://git-scm.com/">git</a>, as well as HTML + CSS consider something else. However, since I am familiar with all of those, it works for me.</p>

<p>The problem is exporting my content from Squarespace. The only export option available is one for <a href="http://wordpress.org/">Wordpress</a>, which dumps everything into an XML file. Since I&rsquo;m not using Wordpress, this didn&rsquo;t work for me. My blog has been quite the sojourner, created orginally on Wordpress, then to Posterous (lol), and finally Squarespace. It&rsquo;s accumulated a bit of cruft. For some reason, older posts did not export properly; if they contained an image and text, the text was deleted.</p>

<p>After some fiddling, I put together a <a href="https://github.com/swilliams/squarespace-exporter">script</a> that would walk each post on the blog, download everything and then move onto the next. I did run into some gotchas though:</p>

<ul>
<li>Some of the older images were named &ldquo;#img.jpg&rdquo;. I ended up <a href="https://github.com/swilliams/squarespace-exporter/blob/master/script.rb#L151">generating</a> a random string for the filename and removing the hashtag.</li>
<li><code>&lt;img&gt;</code> tags used a <code>data-src</code> attribute instead of a standard <code>src</code> attribute. <a href="https://github.com/swilliams/squarespace-exporter/blob/master/script.rb#L181">The fix was to rename the attribute</a>.</li>
<li>There was a veritable boatload of extra markup and attributes on each post, which made things look weird. I ended up parsing the entire HTML of each post and <a href="https://github.com/swilliams/squarespace-exporter/blob/master/script.rb#L223">stripping</a> out all the unnecessary stuff.</li>
</ul>


<p>There are still some issues that I&rsquo;ll need to address on a case by case basis, but it&rsquo;s a good 80% solution right now.</p>

<p><figure></p>

<pre><code>&lt;img src="http://swilliams.github.io/images/assets/octopress.png" alt="Octopress" /&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></figure></p>

<p>I like Octopress because it is fast, easy for me to manage, and keeps my content in a simple (and portable) format. I just hope that this will last me for a while. It doesn&rsquo;t do nearly as many things as Squarespace, but most of those I don&rsquo;t need.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Demystifying Ruby DSLs — Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://swilliams.github.io/words/2014/02/21/demystifying-ruby-dsls-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://swilliams.github.io/words/2014/02/21/demystifying-ruby-dsls-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/words/2014/01/26/demystifying-ruby-dsls">Last time we learned about how to use modules to dynamically add functionality to a class</a>. This time let&rsquo;s take a look at doing that, but customizing our extensions at runtime.</p>

<p>What helped me ultimately understand how these things work is that you are building up classes on the fly. It&rsquo;s kind of like when you <code>include</code> a module, it&rsquo;s editing that class to add more methods to it. Think of a bunch of Legos. Each Lego is a module with various methods on it. At runtime they assemble together to build a castle.</p>

<p><figure></p>

<pre><code>&lt;img alt="Lego Castle by InSapphoWeTrust on Flickr." src="http://swilliams.github.io/images/assets/lego-annotated.png"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/56619626@N05/7406185206/in/photolist-chsCQo-chsDcG-chsCVb-chsD97-chsBY3-chsCeN-chsDid-bgETZB-8FZGC9-9nsJ9P-8oTk1n-dCdMj4-f8b3QR-7J1LqD-7BnYDa-7BnZmZ-7BrJZw-7BrLsb-7BnVLP-9XN1mi-cnFar5-chsCy7-gC3qkX-chsCKW-chsCs1-chsCoN-aCZJqe-aCZJe4-chsCcf-chsC41-aCcgjW-aC9BwX-aCcgf3-aC9BE6-aC9BKr-aCcgUf-aCcgRw-aC9C9v-aCcgXo-chsC7J-chsBZw-a5YVbT-em9rGR-em9ru8-emfdMW-em9tEg-emfewq-emfeEm-emfdxf-emfeh9-emfdi5"&gt;Lego Castle&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/skinnylawyer/"&gt;InSapphoWeTrust&lt;/a&gt; on Flickr.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></figure></p>

<h3>Dynamically Adding</h3>

<p>What if those Legos could generate even more Legos as you were building with them, and then intelligently join themselves together?</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re familiar with Rails, you&rsquo;ve seen that you can just declare associations within a model — <code>:has_many</code>, <code>:has_one</code>, and so on. Once you add those directives to your class, suddenly you have access to brand spanking new methods. Have you ever wondered how that worked? Let&rsquo;s implement a rudimentary version.</p>

<p>Think for a moment about <code>:has_many</code>. What would you expect the line <code>has_many :gerbils</code> methods to do?  You would have to have a <code>gerbils</code> method to retrieve the little fellas, and another one, <code>gerbils=(new_value)</code> to set them (and others to add them and so on, but <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keep_it_simple_stupid">KISS</a>). You implement that with a generic <code>get_child_models(child_name)</code> method, but that feels like the Java (™ Oracle Corporation) way&hellip; and I have too much self respect to go down that path. Instead we can take advantage of Ruby&rsquo;s metaprogramming capabilities and generate them dynamically.</p>

<p>One way to do this is with <code>eval</code>.</p>

<h3>A Word on Eval</h3>

<p>Ruby has a few versions of <code>eval</code>. They all take strings or blocks and turn them in code that is executed.</p>

<ul>
<li>There&rsquo;s the <a href="http://www.ruby-doc.org/core-2.1.0/Kernel.html#method-i-eval">standard one</a> that executes arbitrary code.</li>
<li><a href="http://ruby-doc.org/core-2.1.0/Module.html#method-i-class_eval">class_eval</a> — similar to vanilla <code>eval</code>, but executes the code in the context of the Class itself. There&rsquo;s also <code>module_eval</code> which does the same thing (more or less). Example:</li>
</ul>


<p>``` ruby
class Monkey
end</p>

<p>m = Monkey.new
Monkey.class_eval %q(def screech() &lsquo;Eek Eek&rsquo; end)
m.screech # Eek Eek
```</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="">instance_eval</a> — modifies a class, but from an instance point of view, <em>and only for that particular instance</em> (this is called a <a href="http://rubymonk.com/learning/books/4-ruby-primer-ascent/chapters/39-ruby-s-object-model/lessons/131-singleton-methods-and-metaclasses">Singleton method</a>).</li>
</ul>


<p>``` ruby
class Monkey
end</p>

<p>m = Monkey.new
m2 = Monkey.new
m.instance_eval %q(def screech() &lsquo;Eek Eek&rsquo; end)
m.screech # Eek Eek
m2.screech # NoMethodError: undefined method `screech' for #&lt;Monkey:0x007fa6f768bac8>
```</p>

<p>Using these techniques you can generate the set of methods for our <code>:has_many</code> implementation.</p>

<p>``` ruby
module Associations
  class &lt;&lt; self</p>

<pre><code>def included(base)
  base.extend Associations::ClassMethods
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  module ClassMethods</p>

<pre><code>def has_many(thingies)
  code = %(
    def #{thingies}
        # retrieve stuff from here
    end

    def #{thingies}=(new_value)
        # set new_value here
    end
  )
  class_eval code
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>Now, if you <code>include Associations</code> in your class, you can call <code>has_many :hamsters</code> or <code>has_many :gerbils</code> or <code>has_many :guinea_pigs</code> and have all of your getters and setters created.</p>

<p><figure></p>

<pre><code>&lt;img alt="This is you with all the gerbil methods." src="http://swilliams.github.io/images/assets/cashew.jpg"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;This is you with all the gerbil methods.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></figure></p>

<h3>Caution</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;m not a big fan of <code>eval</code>, at least when using it with strings. The biggest reason is that it makes bugs harder to find. The Ruby interpreter will point out syntax errors when the file loads, but a typo in an evalled string won&rsquo;t get caught until runtime. The longer the string, the more likely something bad will creep in there. And some of these dynamically created methods will be long. I&rsquo;m talking <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0026L7H20/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B0026L7H20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=thepetzoo-20">Lord of the Rings Extended Edition</a> long.</p>

<p>Fortunately there is a better way. The eval methods also take blocks, which work pretty well in most cases. For the purposes of dynamically generating methods, I prefer using <code>define_method</code> <a href="http://ruby-doc.org/core-2.1.0/Module.html#method-i-define_method">source</a>. It&rsquo;s available on <code>Module</code> (and therefore classes too) and, just like it says on the tin, is designed to create methods on the fly and add them to a class.</p>

<p>``` ruby
def has_many(thingies)
  define_method thingies.to_s do</p>

<pre><code># retrieve stuff from here
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  define_method &ldquo;#{thingies}=&rdquo; do</p>

<pre><code># set new_value here
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s kinda similar to the eval code, in fact, <code>define_method</code> passes itself along to <code>instance_eval</code>, so when all is said and done, it&rsquo;s merely for our convenience. But is easier to test, and will complain loudly if there&rsquo;s a syntax error.</p>

<p>Working with actual code rather than a string makes refactoring easier too. Let&rsquo;s say you want to enable your users to define their own implementations of the generated rodent methods. Pulling that out into its own method is simple:</p>

<p>``` ruby
def add_method_without_clobbering (method_name, &amp;method_definition)
  unless method_defined? method_name</p>

<pre><code>define_method method_name, method_definition
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>def has_many(thingies)
  add_method_without_clobbering thingies.to_s do</p>

<pre><code># retrieve stuff from here
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  add_method_without_clobbering &ldquo;#{thingies}=&rdquo; do</p>

<pre><code># set new_value here
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s still possible with string evals, but is easier to read in my eyes.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;ll wrap up this entry on DSLs. There&rsquo;s only one other big piece of the pie I&rsquo;d like to cover — blocks, but you can do a whole lot without them.</p>

<p>One thing to keep in mind when writing DSLs is that it can be hard to follow along. Document everything, especially the esoteric parts. It might even be a good idea to diagram the path of all the <code>include</code> chain. DSLs can make client code easier to write, but usually at the expense of crazy complexity within the DSL itself.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Demystifying Ruby DSLs]]></title>
    <link href="http://swilliams.github.io/words/2014/01/26/demystifying-ruby-dsls/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://swilliams.github.io/words/2014/01/26/demystifying-ruby-dsls</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I like <a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a>. It has a way of appearing clean and simple, while still being expressive. Due to its <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_typing#Dynamic_type-checking_and_runtime_type_information">typing system</a> you can bend it in a variety of ways to do certain things that would be very complicated in other languages, or make you write an entire compiler. I&rsquo;m talking, of course, about Domain Specific Languages, or <a href="http://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_specific_language">DSLs</a>. If you&rsquo;ve ever used a popular Ruby library (like Rails, or RSpec, or anything else) then you&rsquo;ve used a DSL. Rails in particular has a couple different ones:</p>

<p>``` ruby
 # Routes
 # config/routes.rb
 DerptyDerp::Application.routes.draw do
   resources :users
   resources :dinguses, only: [:new, :show]
 end</p>

<p> # ActiveRecord
 # app/models/user.rb
 class User &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
   validates :email, presence: true, uniqueness: true
   has_one :dingus, dependent: :destroy
 end
```</p>

<p>And so on. At first glance, the code that allows this can be intimidating, especially when it&rsquo;s been broken up and refactored across 20 different classes and modules. Fortunately, there are probably only about 10 things that you really need to know to read along, and to make them yourself.</p>

<h3>Class Methods</h3>

<p>Did you know that you can execute code right from within a class declaration? Well, you can. Try it!</p>

<p>``` ruby
class Derp
  def self.can_eat_sandwiches</p>

<pre><code>puts "I LOVE CATS"
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  can_eat_sandwiches
end
```</p>

<p>When that class is read by the interpreter, it&rsquo;ll execute the <code>can_eat_sandwiches</code> method and print the non-sequitur to the console. This&rsquo;ll even work through inheritance.</p>

<p><code>ruby
class Herp &lt; Derp
  can_eat_sandwiches
end
</code></p>

<p>And you&rsquo;ll have a wonderful message printed out twice. This technique can be used to do more than just clutter up a log file too! For example, in Rails when you <a href="https://github.com/rails/rails/blob/9c025ab6e9731dde56186b41ba5d4f216a48c831/activemodel/lib/active_model/validations.rb#L140">setup validation</a>, all you&rsquo;re doing is calling another method.</p>

<h3>Put it into a Module</h3>

<p>Sometimes you want to add functionality to a class without locking it into a long inheritance chain. Ruby uses <a href="http://www.tutorialspoint.com/ruby/ruby_modules.htm">Modules</a> to accomplish this, so you can pull your methods into a separate file to include them at will. There&rsquo;s a catch though before you dive in. Traditionally, you&rsquo;d include a module like this:</p>

<p>``` ruby
module TheHerppening
  def can_eat_sandwiches
  end
end</p>

<p>class Sandwichable
  include TheHerppening
end
```</p>

<p>If you know how modules work, you might&rsquo;ve noticed that will only add <code>can_eat_sandwiches</code> to <em>instances</em> of <code>Sandwichable</code>, not to <code>Sandwichable</code> itself. Which means that calling <code>can_eat_sandwiches</code> directly in the class won&rsquo;t work. But fear not! Ruby can be molded in many dark and fearsome ways. Rather than using <code>include</code>, you can use <code>extend</code> to add methods to a class.</p>

<p>``` ruby
class Sandwichable
  extend TheHerppening</p>

<p>  can_eat_sandwiches
end
```</p>

<p>Aaaaand we&rsquo;re back in business. But, say you wanted to have some methods that needed to be on instances, and some for the class? Can you mix both? Sure. Just wrap them in different modules and add them with the appropriate calls. There&rsquo;s even a pattern to follow for naming the modules: <code>ClassMethods</code> and <code>InstanceMethods</code>:</p>

<p>``` ruby
module TheHerppening
  module ClassMethods</p>

<pre><code>def can_eat_sandwiches
  puts 'DING'
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  module InstanceMethods</p>

<pre><code>def eat_the_sandwich
  puts 'I wish I could marry a sandwich.'
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>They can even be in the same file. As a side note, this is also how you can do namespacing in Ruby. Including these can be a little tedious if you have to add this to lots of classes.</p>

<p>``` ruby
class Sandwichable</p>

<pre><code>extend TheHerppening::ClassMethods
include TheHerppening::InstanceMethods

can_eat_sandwiches
</code></pre>

<p>end
```</p>

<p>Not to mention ugly. And if there&rsquo;s one thing a good Ruby coder can&rsquo;t stand, it&rsquo;s ugly code. Let&rsquo;s fix that.</p>

<p><a href="http://ruby-doc.org/core-2.1.0/Module.html">Modules</a> (and classes) have all kinds of meta-programming capabilities built in. I encourage you to go and peruse them at your leisure. What we&rsquo;ll focus on here is the <code>[included](http://ruby-doc.org/core-2.1.0/Module.html#method-i-included)</code> method.</p>

<p>``` ruby
module Dingus
  class &lt;&lt; self</p>

<pre><code>def included(base)
  base.send :include, Dingus::InstanceMethods
  base.extend Dingus::ClassMethods
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end
```</p>

<p>All of a sudden, your class now has all of the extra stuff from the <code>Dingus</code> module inside it.</p>

<p>That might be jumping ahead a few steps, what with the <code>class &lt;&lt; self</code> and all. Don&rsquo;t forget that in Ruby, <em>everything</em> is a class, even modules. Conceptually it might be easier to understand if you look at <code>Module</code>&rsquo;s ancestors:</p>

<p>``` ruby</p>

<blockquote><p>Module.ancestors
=> [Module, Object, PP::ObjectMixin, Kernel, BasicObject]
```</p></blockquote>

<p>So, a <code>Module</code> is just a subclass of <code>Object</code> and can be treated as such. <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WFNEgdwjEhs">Whoa</a>. Specifically, the <code>class &lt;&lt; self</code> allows you to put class level methods on the module (you can also do this to a class as an alternative to <code>def self.whatevers</code>).</p>

<p>``` ruby
module Dingus
  class &lt;&lt; self</p>

<pre><code>def say_hi
  puts 'HI'
end
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>Dingus.say_hi # HI
```</p>

<p>And, <code>included</code> is called when that module is included in a class. This means you can set off a chain reaction of includes with just a single one.</p>

<p>This is just the start. Ruby gives you enough metaprogramming rope to build a hammock and then hang yourself with the leftovers. We&rsquo;ll get into some of the other ways to do this later on, including <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/q/4911353/736">blocks</a>, <a href="http://www.ruby-doc.org/core-2.1.0/Kernel.html#method-i-eval">eval</a>, and the infamous <a href="http://www.ruby-doc.org/core-2.1.0/BasicObject.html#method-i-method_missing">method-missing</a>. I encourage you to start digging into some code, and even trying a little of this yourself. Once you get a few reps in, understanding how DSLs work becomes much easier.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Handling Bluetooth Keyboard Events With Modifier Keys in iOS 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://swilliams.github.io/words/2013/09/19/handling-keyboard-events-with-modifier-keys-in-ios-7/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://swilliams.github.io/words/2013/09/19/handling-keyboard-events-with-modifier-keys-in-ios-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div><div><div>
<div><div>
<p>Before iOS 7, if you had a Bluetooth keyboard attached to your iPad, you could only access modifier keys (Command, Control, etc) through <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/14791056/ios-how-to-detect-the-escape-control-keys-on-a-hardware-bluetooth-keyboard">private APIs</a>. You could sneak it in through <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/14940898/736">selector trickery</a> and allegedly Apple would turn a blind eye. Fortunately with iOS 7, there's now a public API to do this.</p>

<p>First, let's talk a bit about the <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/EventHandling/Conceptual/EventHandlingiPhoneOS/event_delivery_responder_chain/event_delivery_responder_chain.html">Responder Chain</a>. This is how events are managed in iOS. Most of the <code>UIKit</code> classes you use inherit from <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/UIKit/Reference/UIResponder_Class/Reference/Reference.html#//apple_ref/occ/cl/UIResponder"><code>UIResponder</code></a> which means that you'll have access to the appropriate methods. This means that you can set the scope for your keyboard shortcuts at any level in the app. I wanted to use have them registered for the entire app, so I subclassed <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/DOCUMENTATION/UIKit/Reference/UIApplication_Class/Reference/Reference.html"><code>UIApplication</code></a>, though you could use a similar approach in a view or the view controller too:</p>
</div></div>
<div><div><pre class="source-code">// STWApplication.h<br>@interface STWApplication : UIApplication {<br>  NSMutableArray *_commands;<br>}<br><br>// STWApplication.m<br>@implementation STWApplication<br>// more coming soon<br>@end</pre></div></div>
<div><div><p>Since we're subclassing <code>UIApplication</code>, edit <code>main.m</code> to tell it that we're doing so in <code>UIApplicationMain</code>:</p></div></div>
<div><div><pre class="source-code">int main(int argc, char *argv[]) {<br>  @autoreleasepool {<br>    NSString *appName = @"STWApplication";<br>    return UIApplicationMain(argc, argv, appName, NSStringFromClass([STWAppDelegate class]));<br>  }<br>}</pre></div></div>
<div><div><p>Ok, now let's tell the app what key combinations are valid. iOS 7 adds a <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/UIKit/Reference/UIResponder_Class/Reference/Reference.html#//apple_ref/occ/instp/UIResponder/keyCommands"><code>keyCommands</code></a> property to UIResponder. All we need to do is override that and returning an array of <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/UIKit/Reference/UIKeyCommand_class/Reference/Reference.html#//apple_ref/occ/cl/UIKeyCommand"><code>UIKeyCommands</code></a>. Since we're using a <code>UIApplication</code> subclass, add this in there:</p></div></div>
<div><div><pre class="source-code">- (NSArray *)keyCommands {<br>  if (!_commands) {<br>    UIKeyCommand *commandF = [UIKeyCommand keyCommandWithInput:@"f"<br>                   modifierFlags:UIKeyModifierCommand<br>                          action:@selector(handleShortcut:)];<br>    _commands = [[NSMutableArray alloc] initWithArray:@[commandF]];<br>  }<br>  return _commands;<br>}<br></pre></div></div>
<div><div><p>Every time a keyboard event is raised, if it matches <kbd>⌘F</kbd>, the selector <code>handleShortcut</code> will be called on the responder chain. That means you can define that method multiple times and only the most specific will be called. For example, if you defined it in <code>STWApplication</code> and in the View Controller, the <code>STWApplication</code> version will <em>never</em> be called. Speaking of <code>handleShortcut</code>, here it is:</p></div></div>
<div><div><pre class="source-code">- (void)handleShortcut:(UIKeyCommand *)keyCommand {<br>  NSLog(@"You pressed ⌘F! Good Job!");<br>}</pre></div></div>
<div><div>
<p><code>UIKeyCommand</code> is pretty neat. The <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/uikit/reference/UIKeyCommand_class/Reference/Reference.html#//apple_ref/doc/c_ref/UIKeyModifierFlags"><code>modifierFlags</code></a> means that the app can watch for Caps Lock, Shift, Control, Alt/Option, Command, and the Number Pad. Additionally, there are some constants that  can be used for special keys like the arrows and Escape. The <a href="">developer forums</a> also had some people getting access to Tab and Return by looking for <code>\t</code> and <code>\r</code>, but I don't know how well those work.</p>

<p>Also, make sure you aren't trying to override system shortcuts. Per the docs: "Key commands that map to known system events (such as cut, copy and paste) are automatically routed to the appropriate responder methods." So don't do that.</p>

<p>Now, remember how I said "every time a keyboard event is raised"? These events will only happen when a text input is the first responder. This means that if you want to have some fancy global shortcuts (say ⌘F to jump to a search box) you'll still need to do a trick with <code>UITextField</code> (or similar). That's a little beyond the scope of this article, but the gist is add a UITextField to a view, hide it, and make sure it stays first responder when appropriate in order to keep firing off those events.</p>

<p>I for one am psyched that this is now available. It's definitely more of a power user feature, but those of us who like to use Bluetooth keyboards with our iPads will derive tremendous benefit from it.</p>
</div></div>
</div></div></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
