<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Podcast | Scott Williams]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/categories/podcast/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-25T07:17:31-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott Williams]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Front to Back #8 — My First Diablo]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2015/02/25/front-to-back-number-8-my-first-diablo/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-25T08:54:52-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2015/02/25/front-to-back-number-8-my-first-diablo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://fronttoback.co/podcast/8">My First Diablo</a> is the newest episode of my <a href="http://fronttoback.co">podcast</a>. It&rsquo;s also the first episode where we have a guest: <a href="http://twitter.com/wickedgood">Steve Lubitz</a> of <a href="http://5by5.tv/isometric">Isometric</a> fame. We talk video games and how that works when you have a bunch of kids in the house. I&rsquo;d wanted to discuss this topic because my kids are now old enough to play console games without getting too frustrated over the experience, and I&rsquo;d been out of the loop for quite some time.</p>

<p>Steve had some solid recommendations and now my wife and I are discussing when would be a good time to re-introduce consoles into the house. That might happen this summer when the kids are done with school, and there will be more time available to figure out limits and such. I&rsquo;m thinking a Wii U would be the right way to go since there&rsquo;s a better selection of kid-friendly games there. What I&rsquo;m not looking forward to is all the controllers/accessories that Nintendo seems to think are required for their games. Most <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Nintendo-Wii-Deluxe-Set-Bundle-3ds/dp/B00MVUKM0A/ref=sr_1_1?sr=8-1&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;keywords=wii%2Bu&amp;tag=thepetzoo-20&amp;qid=1424881179">bundles for the Wii U</a> come with the controller with a screen on it. I can&rsquo;t tell if you can buy more of those or not<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. But you can get <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Nintendo-Wii-Remote-Plus-Black/dp/B00N4OAELY/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;sr=1-1&amp;s=videogames&amp;keywords=wii%2Bmote&amp;tag=thepetzoo-20&amp;qid=1424881298">Wii-motes</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Nintendo-Nunchuk-Controller-Black-Wii/dp/B0094X1ZXU/ref=pd_bxgy_vg_img_y?tag=thepetzoo-20">nunchucks</a>, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Nintendo-Pro-Controller-Black-Wii-u/dp/B00MUY0OFU/ref=pd_sim_vg_3?refRID=0SQ5Z19AHMG8VE30V0TD&amp;tag=thepetzoo-20&amp;ie=UTF8">pro controllers</a>, and various third party gizmos. I&rsquo;m not exactly looking forward to sifting through exactly what kind of those we&rsquo;ll need, nor storing them. I&rsquo;m not even going to touch handheld systems.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>Video games were a big part of my childhood (some might say obsessive&hellip; I had a subscription to Nintendo Power without owning a Nintendo system). My hope is that rather than just consuming all the video game minutiae like I did, my kids will just have fun playing them with their family and friends.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li class="footnote" id="fn:1">
  <p>Amazon and other retailers seem to be sold out of official ones.</p>
</li>
<li class="footnote" id="fn:2">
  <p>Scientifically speaking, there are 327 different versions of the Nintendo DS to choose from.</p>
</li>
  </ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Podcast Appearances]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2015/01/28/podcast-appearances/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-28T14:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2015/01/28/podcast-appearances</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Podcasts are Important Business. Here&rsquo;s an update.</p>

<h3>Better Know a Jackal</h3>

<p>The [rabid] fans of the 5by5 podcast network are informally known as &ldquo;Jackals&rdquo;. One of said Jackals, <a href="http://twitter.com/mikebeasterfeld">Mike Beasterfeld</a> had the brilliant idea to create a <a href="http://www.jackals.us/better-know-a-jackal">podcast to interview us</a>. I made it onto <a href="http://www.jackals.us/better-know-a-jackal/28">episode 28</a>. It&rsquo;s a nice little bio that you can use to gather information to steal my identity.</p>

<h3>Less Than Or Equal</h3>

<p>I was a guest on episode 25 of <a href="http://twitter.com/aleen">Aleen Simms&rsquo;s</a> <a href="http://www.lessthanorequal.com/episodes/25">Less Than Or Equal</a> podcast. I had a great time talking with her and we chatted about maturity, growing up, and how having daughters changed me; specifically some specific incidents in my personal history that formed me into what I am today. Speaking of daughters&hellip;</p>

<h3>Front to Back</h3>

<p>We just released our <a href="http://www.fronttoback.co/podcast/2015/1/27/6-practice-kid">6th(!) episode</a>. I&rsquo;ve really enjoyed making this show and have learned more and more about audio editing. This time around I used some <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_range_compression">compression</a> to make our voices sound better.</p>

<p>Please check them out!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Things I Learned When Making a Podcast]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/03/things-i-learned-when-making-a-podcast/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-03T07:42:25-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/03/things-i-learned-when-making-a-podcast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We just published episode 2 of <a href="https://scott-williams-bc50.squarespace.com/podcast/2014/12/3/2-the-proliferation-of-duplo">the podcast</a>. I&rsquo;m still very new at this, but I&rsquo;ve already learned more than I anticipated. Most of these are forehead slappers that now you can avoid when you make your podcast.</p>

<p>If you want to do a <a href="http://thepodcastersstudio.com/tps-ep-47-recording-a-double-ender-podcast/">double-ender</a>, don&rsquo;t use Quicktime&rsquo;s built-in audio recording &ndash; it smushes all the audio into a single track. <a href="http://www.ecamm.com/mac/callrecorder/">Ecamm Call Recorder</a> or <a href="https://rogueamoeba.com/piezo/">Piezo</a> will keep them separate.</p>

<p>Have each person say something like &ldquo;Recording&rdquo; when they start recording their end of the call. This makes it orders of magnitude easier to line up the separate audio tracks during post production. <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Plug your headphones directly into your microphone. Doing something else will likely lead to some nasty <a href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/02/how-to-add-a-noise-gate-in-garageband-10/">headphone bleed</a>.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re using a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Blue-Microphones-Yeti-USB-Microphone/dp/B002VA464S/ref=sr_1_1?sr=8-1&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;keywords=blue%2Byeti&amp;tag=thepetzoo-20&amp;qid=1417634348">Blue Yeti</a>, switch to Cardioid mode. It&rsquo;s the &ldquo;heart&rdquo; or &ldquo;pacman&rdquo; symbol. Turn the gain down on it too.</p>

<p>You need to <a href="https://www.apple.com/itunes/podcasts/specs.html">submit your podcast feed to Apple</a> if you want your podcast to be in iTunes (and you really want that). According to their <a href="https://www.apple.com/itunes/podcasts/creatorfaq.html">FAQ</a> it can take 24 hours for that feed to be approved. But if you submit your feed on a common US holiday week, like say the Monday before Thanksgiving, it might take significantly longer.</p>

<p>If you have something pre-made you want to say on air, write it down first because your brain will simply refuse to cooperate if you try to just remember it.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li class="footnote" id="fn:1">
  <p>Got this via <a href="http://www.theincomparable.com/theincomparable/">The Incomparable</a>, one of my absolute favorites.</p>
</li>
  </ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Add a Noise Gate in GarageBand 10]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/02/how-to-add-a-noise-gate-in-garageband-10/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-02T09:11:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/02/how-to-add-a-noise-gate-in-garageband-10</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>GarageBand is a decent amateur audio editor and is also free. I use it to edit <a href="http://fronttoback.co">my podcast</a>, which has worked out ok.</p>

<p>Dealing with audio buzzing or humming can be a problem. Sometimes this can be <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spill_%28audio%29">headphone bleed</a>, or ambient noise, or anything. A <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noise_gate">noise gate</a> can fix that up pretty well if it isn&rsquo;t too loud<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. What a noise gate does is analyze your audio and mutes any sound that is below a certain volume. GarageBand has this built-in but it is a little hard to find. It&rsquo;s interface has changed over different versions, so googling around for it often yields out of date information. Here is where it is in version <strong>10</strong>.</p>

<p>First click this knobby button.</p>

<p><figure class="center"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;img alt="knobby button" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/gb/knob.png"&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></figure></p>

<p>This&rsquo;ll bring up a panel at the bottom with some additional controls. Click the information &ldquo;i&rdquo; button, turn off &ldquo;Master&rdquo;, and click &ldquo;Controls&rdquo; from the segmented control.</p>

<p><figure class="center"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;img alt="controls" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/gb/controls.png"&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></figure></p>

<p>Finally, you&rsquo;ll have a checkbox labeled &ldquo;Noise Gate&rdquo; in that info side panel. Check it to turn it on, and use the slider to adjust how big of a gate you want.</p>

<p><figure class="center"></p>

<pre><code>&lt;img alt="noise gate" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/gb/noise-gate.png"&gt;
</code></pre>

<p></figure></p>

<p>This will set the gate on the <em>entire</em> track that is selected up in the main UI. You can have different gates for different tracks, but I don&rsquo;t think you can different ones on a single track in GarageBand.</p>

<p>Once I scrape together a little more cash I might go out and get <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/logic-pro-x/id634148309?mt=12&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11lxUn">Logic Pro</a>. For now though, GarageBand works well enough.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li class="footnote" id="fn:1">
  <p>Shoutout to <a href="https://twitter.com/jmetzendorf">Jim Metzendorf</a> for helping me out with this.</p>
</li>
  </ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My New Podcast]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/01/my-new-podcast/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-01T14:37:23-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/12/01/my-new-podcast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been a fan of podcasts for ages. I listened to <a href="http://grantland.com/podcasts/bs-report/">Bill Simmons&rsquo;s show</a> since it was called &ldquo;Eye of the Sports Guy&rdquo;. I listened to <a href="http://5by5.tv">Dan Benjamin&rsquo;s</a> shows before he made 5by5. About half of my t-shirts are ads for podcasts. So, when some friends asked if I wanted to make a podcast, I jumped at the chance.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a show about fathers raising their daughters. Our discussions range from the goofy stuff our girls do, to the idea that we need to maintain our masculinity being the sole male in the family, to heavier topics. We&rsquo;re calling it <a href="http://fronttoback.co">Front to Back</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. You can get it on <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/front-to-back/id945174610?mt=2">iTunes here</a>.</p>

<p><figure class="pull-right">
  <a href="http://fronttoback.co"><img alt="Front to Back art" src="http://blog.swilliams.me/images/assets/f2b-art.png" /></a>
</figure></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m co-hosting it along with my Internet friends <a href="http://jeffmueller.net">Jeff</a> and <a href="http://samdavies.me">Sam</a>. Right now we are aiming to record every other week. The first episode is a shade over half an hour, which seems like a pretty good duration to me.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s gonna be a learning experience too. Going into this, none of us had ever recorded a podcast. I&rsquo;ve already learned more than I expected about production and audio editing. Watch this space because I&rsquo;m going to write about that process too. We&rsquo;re going to make a bunch of mistakes, but I think we have something here.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li class="footnote" id="fn:1">
  <p>Yeah, it references *that*.</p>
</li>
  </ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
