<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Customer-sat | Scott Williams]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/categories/customer-sat/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-24T20:20:42-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott Williams]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Great Moments in Customer Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2015/07/24/great-moments-in-customer-service/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-24T09:02:27-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2015/07/24/great-moments-in-customer-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/10/15/the-best-customer-service/">Great Customer Service is not dead</a>! When I was doing freelance/independent work I used <a href="https://www.getharvest.com/">Harvest&rsquo;s</a> Solo plan to track my time and invoice clients. It was affordable for a single person and wasn&rsquo;t over-engineered. Since it was cheaper in the long run I paid for a yearly plan and renewed each time it came up. I would&rsquo;ve recommended them to anyone in a similar position. Now I&rsquo;ll recommend them even more heavily.</p>

<p>A few months ago I took a full-time position and just didn&rsquo;t need the paid account any more. I couldn&rsquo;t figure out how to downgrade though so I sent a request to their customer service. The page told me to expect a response within an hour. Within 5 minutes I got a response from Jennifer telling me that my plan had been downgraded to the free one, AND they refunded the prorated amount for the remainder of the year back to me.</p>

<p>Getting a refund wasn&rsquo;t even on my radar. I was perfectly happy with keeping the paid plan and just not renewing it when the time came. What I love about this is that Harvest didn&rsquo;t waffle around the issue for a long time only to end up doing the bare minimum to get the customer to go away. They were fast, proactive, and exceeded expectations.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s how you do customer service.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
