<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Customer-service | Scott Williams]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/categories/customer-service/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-03T19:56:04-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott Williams]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best Customer Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/10/15/the-best-customer-service/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-15T11:09:22-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/10/15/the-best-customer-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few years ago I was at a steakhouse for a company dinner. I had ordered the King of Steaks, a Rib-Eye medium rare and was looking forward to eating it. When I cut into my steak I saw that it was basically well-done (there was the tiniest sliver of pink left amidst a sea of gray). I flagged the server and said &ldquo;Um, I ordered this medium-rare&hellip;&rdquo;<sup>1</sup></p>

<p>Without a moment&rsquo;s hesitation she apologized, grabbed the plate and went directly back to the kitchen with it. Barely five minutes later she brought back out a piping hot steak that was cooked <em>perfectly</em>. She checked back again a few minutes later to make sure everything was ok (it was).</p>

<p>Why was this so good? She knew exactly what had happened and knew how to fix it to my satisfaction. There weren&rsquo;t any games played, just immediate and decisive action.</p>

<p>I was at a hotel recently and the last day something bad happened that left a sour taste in my mouth. The manager on duty very nice and apologetic. But she asked &ldquo;What would you like me to do to &lsquo;make it right&rsquo;?&rdquo;. I hate that question because I don&rsquo;t know how to respond. Asking to comp the whole trip would be overboard and unfair. But putting the onus of the decision on me when I&rsquo;m already under duress only compounds the problem.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re in the service industry, you need to understand what that means and not make the customer come up with their own solutions.</p>

<p><div class="footnotes">
<p><small>
1. There could&rsquo;ve been a dozen reasons why my steak was overcooked, and it probably wasn&rsquo;t the server&rsquo;s fault, so there&rsquo;s no use in getting angry with her about it. The best part is that I didn&rsquo;t even have time to get angry.
</small></p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
