<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sports | Scott Williams]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/categories/sports/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/"/>
  <updated>2018-10-23T10:12:24-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott Williams]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sympathy for the Carroll]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2015/02/02/sympathy-for-the-carroll/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-02T19:04:14-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2015/02/02/sympathy-for-the-carroll</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When listening to a podcast, the host will often forget a word or well known fact. Maybe they&rsquo;ll say something silly like <a href="http://on.cc.com/1rU1N7O">&ldquo;Jedi mind meld&rdquo;</a>. Everyone in the audience knows exactly what they meant, and everyone will likely make that fact known (I&rsquo;ve sure been there, and will likely continue to be).</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wNq8-4DtvaM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Now that I&rsquo;ve released a few episodes of <a href="http://www.fronttoback.co/">my own podcast</a> I&rsquo;ve seen the other side of the microphone. Talking and thinking at the same time is surprisingly difficult after say, 8 words in. I&rsquo;ll find myself stumbling over witty quips and forgetting familiar things that had been otherwise seared into my memory.</p>

<p>So, I have a teensy bit more empathy for Pete Carroll the day after <a href="http://grantland.com/the-triangle/super-bowl-new-england-patriots-seattle-seahawks/">an impressive Super Bowl Loss</a>. Yeah, he probably should&rsquo;ve run Marshawn Lynch on that one play, but I don&rsquo;t know if I would&rsquo;ve had the brain power to make a different decision with under 30 seconds left, in the 4th quarter, of the Super Bowl.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Performance Detractors]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/09/04/performance-detractors/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-04T09:07:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.swilliams.me/words/2014/09/04/performance-detractors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>PED&rsquo;s are one of the long-time kerfuffles in sports. I had a thought about how to solve that controversy the other day.</p>

<p>First, embrace PEDs. Stop suspending athletes for taking them and make everything public. <em>Just pay them less.</em> If PEDs make the game easier for them, don&rsquo;t pay them as much.</p>

<p>Next, encourage Performance <em>Detractors</em> by paying athletes more for using them. If a linebacker can make 15 sacks while on 20mg of Valium, he should be paid more. You could have a whole range.</p>

<ul>
<li>-50% for the horse steroids used by the East Germans in the 80s</li>
<li>-30% for the Lance Armstrong&rsquo;s Blood Doping Special</li>
<li>-20% for all the Biogensis type stuff</li>
<li>-1% for Ibuprofen</li>
<li>Control group. No drugs at all.</li>
<li>+10% Marijuana</li>
<li>+20% Benzodiazepines</li>
<li>+40% LSD</li>
</ul>


<p>Because who wouldn&rsquo;t be entertained by a bunch of oversized men tripping on LSD trying to play football? Roger Goodell, you can use the links in the left sidebar to contact me for terms on where to send a check.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
